Finding Aid for Arnold Transit Company records, 1854-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arnold Transit Company records 1854-1987, 1900-1970
Arnold Transit Company.
24 oversize volumes
14.8 linear feet (in 16 boxes)
2008126 Bb 2
The Arnold Transit Company is the longest operating ferry line on the straits of Mackinac. Founded in 1878 by George T. Arnold, the line continues to transport thousands of passengers and tons of freight every year. The record group consists primarily of early financial records, various property interests of Arnold Transit, and the estates of the Arnold family.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Arnold Transit Company (donor no. 9879 ) in 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
In the late nineteenth century, George T. Arnold and his partners, Francis B. Stockbridge and O.Q. Johnson founded the Mackinac Lumber Company. The timing was fortuitous: the straits were a place of growth that manifested itself in new business ventures, shops, homes along the bluffs of Mackinac Island and the shores of Lake Michigan and Lake Huron. Arnold knew he would need reliable marine transportation to facilitate this growth, so in 1878 he formed--with L.B. Coats--the Arnold and Coats Ferry Line. This first company struggled through 1909, but saw little profit. After raising more stock to purchase the Iroquois and Chippewa, (adding to the ships the Algomah and the Perry) he started the Arnold Transit Company.
Passenger-line travel hit its peak around 1900, especially with travel to and from the Upper Peninsula of Michigan and the popularity of the nearby Les Cheneaux Islands as a resort area. When George Arnold died in 1921, Otto W. Lang arrived from Chicago to audit the company's books, and would prove to be an integral part of the company.
Mrs. Arnold then asked a local attorney, Prentiss M. Brown, Sr. to assist with the handling of the boat company's affairs. When Mrs. Arnold died a few years later, the Arnold heirs were ready to sell their interests in the ferry line. Lang and Brown wanted to keep the entire operation together, and so they bought out the interests in 1935.
Right around this time was a combination of events that led to the downfall of passenger shipping. Strict Congressional regulations on shipping were passed in response to the burning of the Morro Castle on the east coast in which many passengers perished. The use of the automobile and increased highway travel reduced demand on ship travel, and the Great Depression forced many of the larger companies into bankruptcy. During this time, Lang and Brown, started the Union Terminal Piers that owned three-fourths of the Arnold Transit Company.
Despite all of these debilitating factors, the Arnold Transit Company managed to stay financially viable, mainly due to the consistent tourist trade of Mackinac Island. After World War II, the company faced major competition from competing lines. Lang and Brown replaced their labor-intensive steamers with diesel-powered boats, operated by five people. By 1963, Arnold Line had seven of these smaller, and more efficient boats crossing the straits in 30-35 minutes.
With the opening of the Mackinac Bridge connecting the Lower and Upper Peninsulas of Michigan in 1957, more people traveled north to vacation. While some enjoy a leisurely crossing the straits, there was an increasing demand for faster and smoother boats. The Arnold Company responded in 1987 when it introduced the first passenger-carrying catamaran to the Great Lakes.
In 1974, Lang retired and shared his shares to the remaining Brown children. More than eighty years after their initial purchase, Prentiss Brown's sons, daughters and grandchildren still own and operate the company.
The record group consists primarily of early financial records, dating back to 1850, before the company was founded. Other records document the various property interests of the Arnold Transit Company (ATC), and the estates of the Arnold family. The vessels themselves are represented through various certificates, manifests, and logs. Historical advertisements of Arnold Transit have been preserved, as well as promotions of the straits of Mackinac and surrounding area in general. Architectural plans, documents of area organizations, information on competing lines, and a fair number of photographs round out the collection.
The record group is comprised of seven series: Administration, Union Terminal Piers, Topical Files, Area Organizations, People, Visual Materials, and Vessels.
Subjects:
Arnold Transit Company.; Ferries--Michigan--Mackinac, Straits of.; Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Mackinac Island Park and Harbor Commission.; Michigan. Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority.; Piers--Michigan.; Union Terminal Piers (Firm)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Arnold Transit Company.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Ferries--Michigan--Mackinac Island.
Genre Terms:
Business records.; Photographs.
- Administration 1900-1978
  The Administration series covers the business facets of ATC, focusing mainly on its finances, property management, and interaction with government agencies.
  - Quarterly Report of Revenue-Traffic to Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC) 1968-1978 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports to Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC)
    - 1911-1912, 1915-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1937-1940, 1949-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 3)
  - Bois Blanc Island Construction 1931-1932 (Box 3)
  - Customs Documents
    - Baggage Declaration and Entry 1965-1970 (Box 3)
    - Canadian Documents 1967 (Box 3)
      (vessels entering and leaving Canada)
    - Clearance Documents
      (Inward and Outward Manifests, Application and Permit to Lade or Unlade Vessels of 5 Net Tons or More and to Allow Unentered Cargo to Remain Upon Wharf Beyond 48-Hour Period)
      - 1956 (Box 3)
      - 1957 (Box 3)
      - 1958 (Box 3)
      - 1959 (Box 3)
    - Declaration of New or Alternate Master of Vessel 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Master's Oath for Renewal of License of Vessel 1953-1967 (Box 3)
    - Monthly Reports of Marine Activities 1950-1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Oath of New or Alternate Master of Vessel 1952-1964 (Box 3)
    - Record of Vessels Engaged in Foreign Trade 1954-1962 (Box 4)
    - Vessel Bonds 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1951-1975 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda
    - Departmental Correspondence 1946-1969 (Box 4)
    - 1981 (Box 4)
    - 1982
      - General (Box 4)
      - Stockholders (Box 4)
    - 1983
      - General (Box 4)
      - Board of Directors (Box 4)
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985
      - General (Box 4)
      - ATCO (Box 4)
      - UTP (Box 4)
    - 1986
      - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Board of Directors (Box 4)
      - UTP (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - Appreciation Letters 1980-1983 (Box 4)
  - Boat Schedules 1961-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Contracts 1956-1966, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Job Descriptions 1981 (Box 4)
  - Financial records
    - Annual Reports 1919-1942 (Box 5)
    - Annual Statements 1936-1969 (Box 5)
    - Day Books
      - June 1901-December 1901 (Volume 1)
      - January 1902-January 1905 (Volume 2)
    - Journals
      - "ATC Journal-Blotter," April 1900-November 1904 (Volume 3)
      - April 1900-January 1906 (Volume 4)
      - January 1902-December 1906 (Volume 5)
      - December 1906-June 1914 (Volume 6)
      - "George T. Arnold Journal and Ledger" 1908-1912 (Volume 7)
        (Mackinac Island and stock list)
      - January 1909-June 1915 (Volume 8)
      - "Revenue Journal" May 1923-March 1926 (Volume 9)
    - Ledgers
      - April 1900-December 1907 (Volume 10)
      - "Ledger 2," 1890-1894 (cargo and clients) (Volume 11)
      - "Ledger 1902-1904" (Volume 12)
      - "Ledger Index" (Volume 13)
      - "Ledger 3 Index" (Volume 14)
      - Summary of Accounts 1893-1917 1910 (Volume 15)
      - "UTO & D Sales Record 1" April 1910-December 1912 (Volume 22)
      - "Geo. T. Arnold Sales Record 2" January 1913-May 1916 (Volume 23)
      - "Geo.T. Arnold Sales Book 3" June 1916-October 1919 (Volume 24)
      - Summary of Accounts 1910-1918 (Volume 16)
      - Ticket Sales 1940-1950 (Volume 17)
      - Monthly Statements 1953-1964 (Box 5)
    - Tariffs
      - Freight 1947-1971 (Box 5)
      - Passengers 1935-1973 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1951-1973 (Box 5)
    - Taxes 1919-1945 (Capital Stock Tax) (Box 5)
    - Vouchers
      - February 1900-June 1908 (starting in 1903 the "Chippewa" and "Elva" are identified) (Volume 18)
      - February 1905-December 1908 (Volume 19)
    - Vessels 1900-1919, 2 folders (Box 5)
      (includes reports, expenditures, etc.)
    - General 1860s-1972 (Box 5)
      (include photocopy of earlier document)
    - Miscellaneous record book: Freight Listing 1905-1918, Local Ticket Sales, 1900-1915, Insurance Policies, 1905-1913 (Volume 20)
  - Insurance (Box 5)
  - Island Transportation Company
    - General Matters 1940-1948 (Box 5)
    - Purchase and Merger 1944-1947 (Box 5)
  - Property Management
    - Anne Cottage 1921 (Box 5)
    - Chippewa Hotel 1922-1957, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Kalamazoo 1912-1925 (Box 5)
    - Les Cheneaux 1875-1966 (Box 5)
    - Grand Hotel Company 1933-1938 (Box 5)
    - Mackinac Land Company 1920-1938, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Mission House Park Plat 1899-1949 (Box 5)
    - Paul Bunyan 1917-1959 (Box 5)
    - Saint Petersburg, Florida 1926-1946 (Box 5)
    - State Park Leases 1911-1922 (Box 5)
- Union Terminal Piers (UTP) 1933-1972
  Union Terminal Piers also contains financial, legal, and property records.
  - Annual Reports to Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC) 1947-1962, 1965-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Annual Statements 1945-1972 (Box 6)
  - Gonzer Case 1942-1952 (Box 6)
    (City of Mackinac Island seeking to collect ferry license fee)
  - Property Management (Box 6)
  - Straits Transit Inc. 1957-1968 (Box 7)
    (mainly documents relating to Straits Transit Inc. vs. UTP; file includes photographs)
  - Relocation of U.S. Coast Guard Station 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1933-1969 (Box 7)
- Topical Files 1892-1973
  The Topical Files document a variety of issues, including architectural plans, historical documents, advertisements, and information on competitors and alternate forms of travel in the straits.
  - Architectural Plans (Box 7)
  - Attendance 1966-1970 (Box 7)
  - Competitor Services 1941-1973 (Box 7)
  - Federal Government
    - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Dock Construction 1959 (Box 7)
      (includes photographs)
    - U.S. Engineer Applications and Permits
      - Mackinac Island Harbor 1927-1970 (Box 7)
      - St. Ignace Harbor 1959, 1969 (Box 7)
    - U.S. Public Health Service Reports 1946-1951 (Box 7)
  - Historical
    - Advertisements 1923-1930 (Box 7)
      (see also Box 11)
    - Legal Documents 1892-1930, 4 folders (Box 7)
      (includes stocks, deeds, bills of sale, etc.)
    - Ticket Samples (Volume 21)
  - Mackinac Island
    - Historical 1913-1949, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (advertisements and other ferry lines, includes a small packet of photographs)
    - Clippings 1928-1937, 1973-1983, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (newspaper articles, advertisements, etc.)
  - Overland Transit 1937-1968 (Box 7)
  - Seafarer's Union 1963-1972 (Box 7)
- Area Organizations 1921-1956
  Area Organizations focuses on the institutions of Mackinac Island, but also contains information on the Mackinac Bridge Authority.
  - Mackinac Island
    - Defense Fund Association 1921-1923, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Park and Harbor Commission (PHC)
      - Pre Organizational Files 1933-1941, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Chicago, Duluth, and Georgian Bay Transit Company 1953-1956 (Box 8)
      - Land Improvement Project 1941 (Box 8)
        (Milton Tootle Correspondence)
      - St. Ignace Taxation of ATC (Box 8)
      - General Files 1941-1948, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Mackinac Straits Bridge Project Alternate Routes Study 1928-1938 (Box 8)
  - Mackinac Bridge Authority 1933-1950, 5 folders
    - Maps and Plans (Box 8)
- People 1854-1962
  The People series covers prominent people within the ATC and Union Terminal Piers organizations. The Arnold family members are represented, with much of their papers relating to their estates. Some correspondence to and from Otto Lang is preserved, as are other extended family members and business contemporaries.
  - Arnold Family
    - George T. Arnold 1903-1925 (Box 9)
      (correspondence and estate)
    - John W. Arnold 1912-1917 (Box 9)
      (estate)
    - Susan B. Arnold
      - Executor's Accounts 1932-1949, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Inventory 1931-1932 (Box 9)
      - Kalamazoo 1932-1945 (Box 9)
        (bank and property)
      - Power of Attorney 1944-1945 (Box 9)
      - Probate Court 1931-1936 (Box 9)
      - Taxes 1932-1936 (Box 9)
      - UTP 1944-1945 (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous 1932-1939 (Box 9)
  - Brueckman, Minnie
    - Contracts 1920 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
      - 1932 (Box 9)
      - 1933 (Box 9)
      - 1934 (Box 9)
    - Estate 1934-1935 (Box 9)
  - Chambers, John T. 1951-1962 (Box 10)
    (property management)
  - Dygert, Ward 1917-1922 (Box 10)
    (correspondence)
  - Lang, O.W.
    - Correspondence 1932-1943
      (arranged alphabetically)
      - A (Box 10)
      - B (Box 10)
      - C-K (Box 10)
      - L-M (Box 10)
      - N-Z (Box 10)
      - 1934-1935, 1937 (Box 10)
      - 1941, 1958 (Box 10)
    - Purchase Contracts 1935-1941 (Box 10)
  - Stockbridge, Betsey A.
    - Correspondence 1866-1913
      - George Arnold 1889-1912 (Box 10)
        (administrator of estate)
      - H.H. Booth 1863-1866 (Box 10)
    - Legal Documents 1854-1917 (Box 10)
      (mostly related to her estate)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains a variety of materials on ships and the island itself; most of the items are in black and white format.
  - Photographs
    - Arnold Transit Company (Box 10)
    - Bismark Repair (Box 10)
    - Mackinac Straits (Box 10)
    - Ships (Box 10)
      (various external shots of various lines)
    - Ships-Internal (Box 10)
      (engine room, seating, helm, etc.)
    - Straits Transit, Inc. (Box 10)
  - [Oversized items described elsewhere] (Box 11)
- Vessels 1896-1976
  The Vessels series contains information about the various ships and boats the Arnold line has used. Documents include bills of sale, ships' logs, certificates of inspection, and correspondence.
  - Ship Logs
    - Algomah, 1964-1971, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - Chippewa, 1922, 1948-1967, 7 volumes (Box 12)
    - Elva, 1929, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - Emerald Isle, 1965-1969, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - Detroit, 1953-1955, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - Fairy Isle, 1953-1958, 2 volumes (Box 13)
    - Huron, 1955-1976, 9 volumes (Box 13)
    - Iroquois, 1955-1962, 3 volumes (Box 14)
      (one volume also contains log of the Emerald Isle)
    - Mackinac Islander, 1958-1971, 10 volumes (Box 14)
    - Mohawk, 1957-1974, 6 volumes (Box 15)
    - Ottawa, 1959-1964, 2 volumes (Box 15)
    - Unidentified 1953, 1974-1976, 2 volumes (Box 15)
  - Other Materials
    - Algomah II, 1952-1962 (Box 16)
    - Chief, 1942-1943 (Box 16)
    - Chippewa 1900-1962 (Box 16)
    - Columbia, 1909 (Box 16)
    - D.P. Perry, 1917-1945 (Box 16)
    - Elva, 1908-1954 (Box 16)
    - Eugene Hart, 1911 (Box 16)
    - Fairy Isle, 1946-1961 (Box 16)
      (formerly the Florence K)
    - Good News, 1941-1942 (Box 16)
    - Iroquois, 1901-1962 (Box 16)
    - Islander, 1909-1934 (Box 16)
      (see also Box 11 for oversize certificates dating from 1896)
    - Mackinac, 1911-1917 (Box 16)
    - Mackinac Islander, 1946 (Box 16)
    - Mary Margaret, 1948-1950 (Box 16)
    - Oliver H. Perry, 1938-1957 (Box 16)
    - Ottawa, 1923-1958 (Box 16)
    - Pilot II, 1942-1945 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)